<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string-array name="game_concepts">
        <item>100. General</item>
        <item>101. The Magic Golden Rules</item>
        <item>102. Players</item>
        <item>103. Starting the Game</item>
        <item>104. Ending the Game</item>
        <item>105. Colors</item>
        <item>106. Mana</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="golden_rules">
        <item>101.1. Whenever a card’s text directly contradicts these rules, the card takes precedence. The card overrides only the rule that applies to that specific situation. The only exception is that a player can concede the game at any time (see rule 104.3a).101.1. Whenever a card’s text directly contradicts these rules, the card takes precedence. The card overrides only the rule that applies to that specific situation. The only exception is that a player can concede the game at any time (see rule 104.3a).</item>
        <item>101.2. When a rule or effect allows or directs something to happen, and another effect states that it can’t happen, the “can’t” effect takes precedence.
Example: If one effect reads “You may play an additional land this turn” and another reads “You can’t play land cards this turn,” the effect that precludes you from playing lands wins.</item>
        <item>101.2a Adding abilities to objects and removing abilities from objects don’t fall under this rule. (See rule 112.10.)</item>
        <item>101.3. Any part of an instruction that’s impossible to perform is ignored. (In many cases the card will specify consequences for this; if it doesn’t, there’s no effect.)</item>
        <item>101.4. If multiple players would make choices and/or take actions at the same time, the active player (the player whose turn it is) makes any choices required, then the next player in turn order (usually the player seated to the active player’s left) makes any choices required, followed by the remaining nonactive players in turn order. Then the actions happen simultaneously. This rule is often referred to as the “Active Player, Nonactive Player (APNAP) order” rule.
Example: A card reads “Each player sacrifices a creature.” First, the active player chooses a creature he or she controls. Then each of the nonactive players, in turn order, chooses a creature he or she controls. Then all creatures chosen this way are sacrificed simultaneously.</item>
        <item>101.4a If an effect has each player choose a card in a hidden zone, such as his or her hand or library, those cards may remain face down as they’re chosen. However, each player must clearly indicate which face-down card he or she is choosing.</item>
        <item>101.4b A player knows the choices made by the previous players when he or she makes his or her choice, except as specified in 101.4a.</item>
        <item>101.4c If a player would make more than one choice at the same time, the player makes the choices in the order written, or in the order he or she chooses if the choices aren’t ordered.</item>
        <item>101.4d If a choice made by a nonactive player causes the active player, or a different nonactive player earlier in the turn order, to have to make a choice, APNAP order is restarted for all outstanding choices.</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="starting_the_game">
        <item>103.1. At the start of a game, each player shuffles his or her deck so that the cards are in a random order. Each player may then shuffle or cut his or her opponents’ decks. The players’ decks become their libraries.</item>
        <item>103.1a If a player is using a sideboard (see rule 100.4) or double-faced cards being represented by checklist cards (see rule 711.9), those cards are set aside before shuffling.</item>
        <item>103.1b In a Commander game, each player puts his or her commander from his or her deck face up into the command zone before shuffling. See rule 903.6.</item>
        <item>103.1c In a Conspiracy Draft game, each player puts any number of conspiracy cards from his or her sideboard into the command zone before shuffling. See rule 905.4.</item>
        <item>103.2. After the decks have been shuffled, the players determine which one of them will choose who takes the first turn. In the first game of a match (including a single-game match), the players may use any mutually agreeable method (flipping a coin, rolling dice, etc.) to do so. In a match of several games, the loser of the previous game chooses who takes the first turn. If the previous game was a draw, the player who made the choice in that game makes the choice in this game. The player chosen to take the first turn is the starting player. The game’s default turn order begins with the starting player and proceeds clockwise.
</item>
        <item>103.2a In a game using the shared team turns option, there is a starting team rather than a starting player.</item>
        <item>103.2b In an Archenemy game, these methods aren’t used to determine who takes the first turn. Rather, the archenemy takes the first turn.</item>
        <item>103.2c One card, Power Play, states that its controller is the starting player. This effect supersedes these methods.</item>
        <item>103.3. Each player begins the game with a starting life total of 20. Some variant games have different starting life totals.</item>
        <item>103.3a In a Two-Headed Giant game, each team’s starting life total is 30.</item>
        <item>103.3b In a Vanguard game, each player’s starting life total is 20 plus or minus the life modifier of his or her vanguard card.</item>
        <item>103.3c In a Commander game, each player’s starting life total is 40.</item>
        <item>103.3d In an Archenemy game, the archenemy’s starting life total is 40.</item>
        <item>Each player draws a number of cards equal to his or her starting hand size, which is normally seven. (Some effects can modify a player’s starting hand size.) A player who is dissatisfied with his or her initial hand may take a mulligan. First, the starting player declares whether or not he or she will take a mulligan. Then each other player in turn order does the same. Once each player has made a declaration, all players who decided to take mulligans do so at the same time. To take a mulligan, a player shuffles his or her hand back into his or her library, then draws a new hand of one fewer cards than he or she had before. If a player kept his or her hand of cards, those cards become the player’s opening hand, and that player may not take any further mulligans. This process is then repeated until no player takes a mulligan. (Note that if a player’s hand size reaches zero cards, that player must keep that hand.)</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="rules">
        <item>1. Game Concepts</item>
        <item>2. Parts of a Card</item>
        <item>3. Card Types</item>
        <item>4. Zones</item>
        <item>5. Turn Structure</item>
        <item>6. Spells, Abilities, and Effects</item>
        <item>7. Additional Rules</item>
        <item>8. Multiplayer Rules</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="player_rules">
        <item>102.1. A player is one of the people in the game. The active player is the player whose turn it is. The other players are nonactive players.</item>
        <item>102.2. In a two-player game, a player’s opponent is the other player.</item>
        <item>102.3. In a multiplayer game between teams, a player’s teammates are the other players on his or her team, and the player’s opponents are all players not on his or her team.</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="parts_of_a_card">
        <item>200. General</item>
        <item>201. Name</item>
        <item>202. Mana Cost and Color</item>
        <item>203. Illustration</item>
        <item>204. Color Indicator</item>
        <item>205. Type Line</item>
        <item>206. Expansion Symbol</item>
        <item>207. Power/Toughness </item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="parts_of_a_card_name">
        <item>201.1. The name of a card is printed on its upper left corner.</item>
        <item>201.3. If an effect instructs a player to name a card, the player must choose the name of a
        card that exists in the Oracle card reference (see rule 108.1) and is legal in the format of
        the game the player is playing. (See rule 100.6.) If the player wants to name a split card,
        the player must choose the name of one of its halves, but not both. (See rule 708.) If the
        player wants to name a flip card’s alternative name, the player may do so. (See rule 709.)
        If the player wants to name the back face of a double-faced card, the player may do so. (See
        rule 711.) A player may not choose the name of a token unless it’s also the name of a card.</item>
        <item>201.4. Text that refers to the object it’s on by name means just that particular object and not any other objects with that name, regardless of any name changes caused by game effects.</item>
        <item>201.5. If an ability of an object uses a phrase such as “this [something]” to identify an object, where [something] is a characteristic, it is referring to that particular object, even if it isn’t the appropriate characteristic at the time.</item>
        <item>202. Mana Cost and Color</item>
        <item>202.1. A card’s mana cost is indicated by mana symbols near the top of the card. (See rule 107.4.) On most cards, these symbols are printed in the upper right corner. Some cards from the Future Sight set have alternate frames in which the mana symbols appear to the left of the illustration.

202.1a The mana cost of an object represents what a player must spend from his or her mana pool to cast that card. Unless an object’s mana cost includes Phyrexian mana symbols (see rule 107.4f), paying that mana cost requires matching the color of any colored mana symbols as well as paying the generic mana indicated in the cost.</item>
        <item>207. Text Box

207.1. The text box is printed on the lower half of the card. It usually contains rules text defining the card’s abilities.</item>
        <item>208. Power/Toughness

208.1. A creature card has two numbers separated by a slash printed in its lower right corner. The first number is its power (the amount of damage it deals in combat); the second is its toughness (the amount of damage needed to destroy it). For example, 2/3 means the object has power 2 and toughness 3. Power and toughness can be modified or set to particular values by effects.</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="parts_of_a_card_generale">
        <item>200.1. The parts of a card are name, mana cost, illustration, color indicator, type line, expansion symbol, text box, power and toughness, loyalty, hand modifier, life modifier, illustration credit, legal text, and collector number. Some cards may have more than one of any or all of these parts.</item>
        <item>200.2. Some parts of a card are also characteristics of the object that has them. See rule 109.3.</item>
        <item>200.3. Some objects that aren’t cards (tokens, copies of cards, and copies of spells) have some of the parts of a card, but only the ones that are also characteristics. See rule 110.5 and rule 706.</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="mtg_tutorials">
        <item>Welcome to the Multiverse</item>
        <item>The Five Colors of Mana</item>
        <item>Game Zones and Parts of a Card</item>
        <item>Card Types</item>
        <item>Parts of a Turn</item>
        <item>The Next Step</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="mana">
        <item>106. Mana</item>

        <item>106.1. Mana is the primary resource in the game. Players spend mana to pay costs, usually when casting spells and activating abilities.</item>
        <item>106.1a There are five colors of mana: white, blue, black, red, and green.</item>
        <item>106.1b There are six types of mana: white, blue, black, red, green, and colorless.</item>
        <item>106.2. Mana is represented by mana symbols (see rule 107.4). Mana symbols also represent mana costs (see rule 202).</item>
        <item>106.3. Mana is produced by the effects of mana abilities (see rule 605). It may also be produced by the effects of spells, as well as by the effects of abilities that aren’t mana abilities.</item>
        <item>106.4. When an effect produces mana, that mana goes into a player’s mana pool. From there, it can be used to pay costs immediately, or it can stay in the player’s mana pool. Each player’s mana pool empties at the end of each step and phase.</item>
        <item>106.4a If a player passes priority (see rule 116) while there is mana in his or her mana pool, that player announces what mana is there. If any mana remains in a player’s mana pool after he or she spends mana to pay a cost, that player announces what mana is still there.</item>
        <item>106.5. If an ability would produce one or more mana of an undefined type, it produces no mana instead.
        Example: Meteor Crater has the ability “{T}: Choose a color of a permanent you control. Add one mana of that color to your mana pool.” If you control no colored permanents, activating Meteor Crater’s mana ability produces no mana.</item>
        <item>106.6. Some spells or abilities that produce mana restrict how that mana can be spent, or have an additional effect that affects the spell or ability that mana is spent on. This doesn’t affect the mana’s type.
        Example: A player’s mana pool contains {1}{U} which can be spent only to pay cumulative upkeep costs. That player activates Doubling Cube’s ability, which reads “{3}, {T}: Double the amount of each type of mana in your mana pool.” The player’s mana pool now has {2}{U}{U} in it, {1}{U} of which can be spent on anything.</item>
        <item>106.7. Some abilities produce mana based on the type of mana another permanent or permanents “could produce.” The type of mana a permanent could produce at any time includes any type of mana that an ability of that permanent would produce if the ability were to resolve at that time, taking into account any applicable replacement effects in any possible order. Ignore whether any costs of the ability could or could not be paid. If that permanent wouldn’t produce any mana under these conditions, or no type of mana can be defined this way, there’s no type of mana it could produce.
        Example: Exotic Orchard has the ability “{T}: Add to your mana pool one mana of any color that a land an opponent controls could produce.” If your opponent controls no lands, activating Exotic Orchard’s mana ability will produce no mana. The same is true if you and your opponent each control no lands other than Exotic Orchards. However, if you control a Forest and an Exotic Orchard, and your opponent controls an Exotic Orchard, then each Exotic Orchard could produce {G}.</item>
        <item>106.8. If an effect would add mana represented by a hybrid mana symbol to a player’s mana pool, that player chooses one half of that symbol. If a colored half is chosen, one mana of that color is added to that player’s mana pool. If a colorless half is chosen, an amount of colorless mana represented by that half’s number is added to that player’s mana pool.</item>
        <item>106.9. If an effect would add mana represented by a Phyrexian mana symbol to a player’s mana pool, one mana of the color of that symbol is added to that player’s mana pool.</item>
        <item>106.10. To “tap a permanent for mana” is to activate a mana ability of that permanent that includes the {T} symbol in its activation cost. See rule 605, “Mana Abilities".</item>

        <item>106.11. One card (Drain Power) puts all mana from one player’s mana pool into another player’s mana pool. (Note that these may be the same player.) This empties the former player’s mana pool and causes the mana emptied this way to be put into the latter player’s mana pool. Which permanents, spells, and/or abilities produced that mana are unchanged, as are any restrictions or additional effects associated with any of that mana.</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="general_rules">
        <item>100.1. These Magic rules apply to any Magic game with two or more players, including two-player games and multiplayer games.</item>
        <item>100.1a A two-player game is a game that begins with only two players.</item>
        <item>100.1b A multiplayer game is a game that begins with more than two players. See section 8, “Multiplayer Rules.”</item>
        <item>100.2. To play, each player needs his or her own deck of traditional Magic cards, small items to represent any tokens and counters, and some way to clearly track life totals.</item>
        <item>100.2a In constructed play (a way of playing in which each player creates his or her own deck ahead of time), each deck must contain at least sixty cards. A constructed deck may contain any number of basic land cards and no more than four of any card with a particular English name other than basic land cards.</item>
        <item>100.2b In limited play (a way of playing in which each player gets the same quantity of unopened Magic product such as booster packs and creates his or her own deck using only this product), each deck must contain at least forty cards. A limited deck may contain as many duplicates of a card as are included with the product.</item>
        <item>100.3. Some casual variants require additional items, such as specially designated cards, nontraditional Magic cards, and dice. See section 9, “Casual Variants".</item>
        <item>100.4. Each player may also have a sideboard, which is a group of additional cards the player may use to modify his or her deck between games of a match.</item>
        <item>100.4a In constructed play, a sideboard may contain no more than fifteen cards. The four-card limit (see rule 100.2a) applies to the combined deck and sideboard.</item>
        <item>100.4b In limited play involving individual players, all cards in a player’s card pool not included in his or her deck are in that player’s sideboard.</item>
        <item>100.4c In limited play involving the Two-Headed Giant multiplayer variant, all cards in a team’s card pool but not in either player’s deck are in that team’s sideboard.</item>
        <item>100.4d In limited play involving other multiplayer team variants, each card in a team’s card pool but not in any player’s deck is assigned to the sideboard of one of those players. Each player has his or her own sideboard; cards may not be transferred between players.</item>
        <item>100.5. There is no maximum deck size.</item>
        <item>100.6. Most Magic tournaments (organized play activities where players compete against other players to win prizes) have additional rules covered in the Magic: The Gathering Tournament Rules (found at Wizards.com/WPN/Events/Rules.aspx). These rules may limit the use of some cards, including barring all cards from some older sets.</item>
        <item>100.6a Tournaments usually consist of a series of matches. A two-player match usually involves playing until one player has won two games. A multiplayer match usually consists of only one game.</item>
        <item>100.6b Players can use the Magic Store  Event Locator at Wizards.com/Locator to find tournaments in their area.</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="colors">
        <item>105.1. There are five colors in the Magic game: white, blue, black, red, and green.</item>
        <item>105.2. An object can be one or more of the five colors, or it can be no color at all. An object is the color or colors of the mana symbols in its mana cost, regardless of the color of its frame. An object’s color or colors may also be defined by a color indicator or a characteristic-defining ability. See rule 202.2.</item>
        <item>105.2a A monocolored object is exactly one of the five colors.</item>
        <item>105.2b A multicolored object is two or more of the five colors.</item>
        <item>105.2c A colorless object has no color.</item>
        <item>105.3. Effects may change an object’s color or give a color to a colorless object. If an effect gives an object a new color, the new color replaces all previous colors the object had (unless the effect said the object became that color “in addition” to its other colors). Effects may also make a colored object become colorless.</item>
        <item>105.4. If a player is asked to choose a color, he or she must choose one of the five colors. “Multicolored” is not a color. Neither is “colorless.”</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="ending_the_game">
        <item>104.1. A game ends immediately when a player wins, when the game is a draw, or when the game is restarted.</item>
        <item>104.2. There are several ways to win the game.</item>
        <item>104.2a A player still in the game wins the game if all of that player’s opponents have left the game. This happens immediately and overrides all effects that would prevent that player from winning the game.</item>
        <item>104.2b An effect may state that a player wins the game. (In multiplayer games, this may not cause the game to end; see rule 104.3h.)</item>
        <item>104.2c In a multiplayer game between teams, a team with at least one player still in the game wins the game if all other teams have left the game. Each player on the winning team wins the game, even if one or more of those players had previously lost that game.</item>
        <item>104.2d In an Emperor game, a team wins the game if its emperor wins the game. (See rule 809.5.)</item>
        <item>104.3. There are several ways to lose the game.</item>
        <item>104.3a A player can concede the game at any time. A player who concedes leaves the game immediately. He or she loses the game.</item>
        <item>104.3b If a player’s life total is 0 or less, he or she loses the game the next time a player would receive priority. (This is a state-based action. See rule 704.)</item>
        <item>104.3c If a player is required to draw more cards than are left in his or her library, he or she draws the remaining cards, and then loses the game the next time a player would receive priority. (This is a state-based action. See rule 704.)</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="card_types">
        <item>300. General</item>
        <item>301. Artifacts</item>
        <item>303. Creatures</item>
        <item>303. Enchantments</item>
        <item>304. Instants</item>
        <item>305. Lands</item>
        <item>306. Planeswalkers</item>
        <item>307. Sorceries</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="zones">
        <item>300. General</item>
        <item>301. Library</item>
        <item>303. Hand</item>
        <item>303. Battlefield</item>
        <item>304. Graveyard</item>
        <item>305. Stack</item>
        <item>306. Exile</item>
        <item>307. Command</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="multiplayer_rules">
        <item>300. General</item>
        <item>301. Limited Range of Influence Option</item>
        <item>303. Attack Multiple Players Option</item>
        <item>303. Attack Left and Attack Right Options</item>
        <item>304. Free-for-All Variant</item>
        <item>305. Grand Melee Variant</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="additional_rules">
        <item>300. General</item>
        <item>301. Keyword Actions</item>
        <item>303. Keyword Abilities</item>
        <item>303. Turn-Based Actions</item>
        <item>304. Flipping a Coin</item>
        <item>305. Leveler Cards</item>
        <item>306. Double-Faced Cards</item>
        <item>307. Controlling Another Player</item>
        <item>307. Taking Shortcuts</item>
        <item>307. Handling Illegal Actions</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="spells">
        <item>300. Casting Spells</item>
        <item>301. Activating Activated Abilities</item>
        <item>303. Handling Triggered Abilities</item>
        <item>303. Handling Static Abilities</item>
        <item>304. Mana Abilities</item>
        <item>305. Loyalty Abilities</item>
        <item>306. Linked Abilities</item>
        <item>307. Resolving Spells and Abilities</item>
        <item>307. Command</item>
        <item>307. Command</item>
        <item>307. Command</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="turn_structure">
        <item>300. Beginning Phase</item>
        <item>301. Untap Step</item>
        <item>303. Draw Step</item>
        <item>303. Main Phase</item>
        <item>304. Combat Phase</item>
        <item>305. Declare Attackers Step</item>
        <item>306. Declare Blockers Step</item>
        <item>306. Combat Damage Step</item>
        <item>306. End of Combat Step</item>
        <item>306. Ending Phase</item>
        <item>307. End Step</item>
    </string-array>
</resources>